本字幕由诸神字幕组(kamigami.org)整理出品 仅供交流学习 禁止用于商业用途
---诸神字幕组---
日文校对: xindylee  SAKURA
总校&后期：Maize
Hello!
こんにちは
Mimi!
How are you?
元気?
入った
Got it!
What a mysterious melody...
不思議な音楽…
Production - CoMix Wave Films
Original Work/Screenplay - Makoto Shinkai
Music - Tenmon
Character Design / Animation Supervisor - Takayo Nishimura
Art - Takumi Tanji
Director  -  Makoto Shinkai
I haven't been able to hear it again...
あれから聴けないね あの唄
Good evening!
こんばんは
Good evening.
Thanks for watching over me.
お見送り ありがと
I'll bring you dinner later, 'kay?
あとでゴハン持ってきてあげるからね
Mom?
お母さん? 今日は早いね
You're home early today!
Oh.
なーんだ 消し忘れ
Forgot to turn off the light.
Dad, I'm home.
ただいま お父さん
どっから入ってきたの?
How did you get in?
Quit it, Mimi!
こら ミミ
Let's give thanks...
いただきます
That sure was a mysterious song.
不思議な唄だったな
ねえ また聴けるかしら
You think I'll be able to hear it again?
Goodnight, Mimi.
おやすみ ミミ
A light?
光った
Maybe it was my imagination...
気のせいかな
Next, Miss Yuu Yazaki.
次 矢崎ユウさん
Keep up the good work.
その調子でね -はい
I will!
Next, Miss Asuna Watase.
次 渡瀬アスナさん
はい
Coming.
Asuna has the best score
in the class once more.
今回もアスナさんがクラスで一番です
またアスナが１位？
She's first again?
You've really been working hard.
よく頑張りましたね
さすが委員長
That's our class rep for ya!
ガリ勉してるもんね一
She's a studyin' machine!
では 最後に注意連絡です
Now then, there's a warning
I need to give you.
Lately there have been reports
from some students
最近 何人かの生徒から
小測のあたりでクマのような動物を見たという報告がありました
about a creature near Obuchi
that looks like a bear.
It was near the railroad bridge...
My brother said he saw it.
鉄橋のとこでさ 俺の兄ちゃんも 見たって言ってたぜ
Just in case, please go straight home.
念のため 寄り道をしないように
Please go home with a friend
that lives near you.
家が近くのお友達と 一緒に帰るようにしてください
Yes, ma'am!
ハーイ
Hey, Asuna!
アースナちゃん 一緒に帰らない？
Want to walk home together?
Oh... Sorry, I have to hurry back.
ごめん 私 ちよっと急がなきゃいけないの
Thanks for asking, though.
誘ってくれて どうもありがとう
Sure... Maybe another time?
うん じゃあ また今度ね
うちの先生も言ってたよ
へー　そんなの…
Five kilos of rice, please.
お米5キロください
Thank you, as always.
いつも ありがとね
Oh, are you all right with that?
あら 大丈夫？
Just fine, thank you!
大丈夫です
What lovely weather...
いい お天気
I can't hear the birds...
鳥が鳴いてない
W-What in the world...
な 何 これ…
Stay away!
やだ
下がって
Stand back.
It'll be okay.
大丈夫
Um...
あの…
Its life is coming to an end.
寿命なんだ
ダメだ
No!
I'm sorry for putting you
in such a scary situation.
怖い思いをさせたよね
ごめん
This is the end, you see.
これで最後だから
U-Um, wait a sec...
あのちょっと
Trust me.
信じて
I'm sure I came here to meet you.
僕はきっと
君に会いにきたんだ
You're awake, I see.
気がついたね
Yeah...
The danger has passed,
so you can return home safely now.
もう危険はないから 安心して家に帰って
Um... You saved me, right?
あの… 助けてくれたんだよね
ありがとう
Thank you!
It'd be best for you not to come
near this mountain any longer.
この山には もう近づかないほうがいい
Mimi?
I know what I saw!
見間違いじゃありませんよ 確かに誰かいたんです
There were definitely people there.
Two kids, about this tall.
このくらいの子供のような
Kids?
子供？
Commander!
中佐
Over here.
こちらへ
Miss Watase?
渡瀬さん？アスナさんはお休み？
Is Asuna absent?
I do hope she's feeling all right...
具合が悪いのかしら 心配ね
Now, I think you all might
have heard already,
さて 皆さん もう聞いたかもしれませんが
昨日 小渕の鉄橋に クマが出たそうです
but that bear appeared yesterday
on the Obuchi Bridge.
We know! A freight train hit it, right?
貨物にぶつかったんでしよ
警察ガ調べてるんだって
I heard the police are investigatin'.
でも もう死んだって
But I heard it's already dead.
Pardon my interruption...
とにかく 通学路の近くでもありますから
It might still be near the routes you take
to school, so take extra special care.
皆さん 十分に気をつけてください
ハーイ
Yes, ma'am!
Yuu, will you tell Asuna for me?
ユウさん アスナさんにも そう伝えてあげて
ハイ
Sure.
それから
Also, the substitute teacher
that'll be filling in for me
私の産休中の代任の先生が明日から引き継ぎに いらっしゃいます
while I'm on leave
will be coming tomorrow.
Is she pretty?
その先生って美人ですか？
Sorry, but it's a man.
残念 男の方よ
A guy?
No, I'm definitely going.
やっぱり行こう
It was the bridge right ahead, I heard...
この先の鉄橋だって
How frightful...
怖いねえ
I heard they already started the
trains up again, they did...
でも汽車はもう再開したってねえ
Well, there's only one every two hours!
そりゃ2時間に1本だもの
Heya, Asuna!
おや アスナちゃん
Hello.
こんにちは
いい日和だねえ
Lovely sunny day, yes?
Yes... Well...
はい じゃ
Oh, Mr. Sato...
あら 佐藤さん
Howdy.
こんにちは
Hey, did you hear? They say that bear
showed up on the Obuchi Bridge!
ねえ　聞きますか　小渕の鉄橋に クマが出たんです
Dead end.  Safety first
It's here!
ありました
This is...
これは
Tree saplings...
若木だ… ヴィータクアの力か
From the power of vita aqua?
It's crystallizing...
結晶化している
Perhaps someone has come up
to the surface.
おそらく 何者かガ地上に来ている
Search the area!
探せ
I figured she would come.
やはり来るのか
Even though I warned her.
忠告したのに
Yeah...
そうだね
Actually, I was hoping she would come, too.
本当は僕も そう望んでいた
I thought I told you not to come.
来ないほうがいいと言ったのに
But...
だって…
Mimi!
Why, you traitor...
何よ 裏切り者 私にしか懐かなかったクセに
You were only supposed to
get along with me!
You no good two timer...
浮気者 節操なし
This... was my place to begin with.
ここは…
もともと 私の場所だもの誰かに来ちゃダメなんて 言われたくない
I don't want anyone telling me
not to come here.
I'm the same way.
僕と同じだ
I came here because I wanted to.
自分が来たいから来た
I'm Shun. It's nice to meet you.
僕はシュン よろしく
I'm... Asuna.
私は… アスナ
あ… ねえ その腕
Your arm!
It's bleeding... ls this from yesterday?
血が出てる もしかして昨日の…
Oh, it's fine.
ああ 平気だよ
But it's my fault that you...
だって私のせいで…
You should get it looked at
in the hospital later.
あとで病院で 診てもらったほうがいいよ
My mom works there.
私の母がそこで働いてるの
It looks like you have everything here.
何でも そろってるんだね
Yeah. But it's the first time this
has ever come in handy.
うん でも役に立ったのは初めて
I kinda wanted my own place,
so I brought things up piece by piece.
自分だけの場所ガ欲しくて 少しずつ運んでたの
You know?
何となく…
And this is the best place for
the tuning into the radio.
それに ここが一番よくラジオが入るんだ
ラジオ？
Radio?
Okay, all finished!
はイ 終わり
ありがとう
Thank you.
Would you like to listen?
聴いてみる？
I use this crystal instead of a diode.
この鉱石ガタイオードの代わりなの
Depending on the weather and time of day,
you can get different signals.
時間によっても天気によっても 受信状態が変わるんだ
Hey, that stone...
あっ ねえ その石…
Got it!
入った
Here.
はい
It's a music program, see?
音楽番組だね
Yeah...
Want some?
食べる？
ありがとう お腹すいてたんだ
Thank you, I was hungry.
Before, just once, I tuned in to
a really mysterious melody...
前にね
一度だけ 不思議な曲が入ったことがあるの
It was a song different from any
music I'd ever known before.
今まで知ってた どの音楽とも違う唄
Almost like it was the sound
of someone's heart itself.
まるで誰かの心が そのまま音になったみたいな
When I heard it, I was both sad
and happy at the same time,
あの時 幸せと悲しみが一緒にやってきて
私は一人きりじゃないんだって 思えたの
and I was able to feel like
I was no longer alone...
It will stay with me, always...
ずっと胸に残ってる
I wish I could hear it once again.
私はもう一度 あれを聴きたいんだ
Shun...?
シュン… くん？
You aren't going to ask me anything, Asuna?
アスナは僕に何も聞かないんだね
きっと いろいろ疑問があるのに
I'm sure you must have many questions.
あのクマみたいな 生き物のこととか
Like what that bear thing was?
Right.
そう
Yeah... But I'm okay for now.
うん でも今はいい 疑問だらけだもん
There's so much to ask...
I bet it'll take a while, so I'll
come back here tomorrow.
すごく長くなりそうだから 明日また ここに来るよ
I came from a different land
named Agartha.
アガルタっていう遠い場所から僕は来たんだ
Agartha...
アガルタ…
A foreign country?
外国？
Yeah.
There was something I wanted to
see, and someone I had to meet.
どうしても見たいものと どうしても会いたかった人がいたから
But now I've accomplished everything
I wanted. I have no regrets.
でも もう思い残すことは何もない
So your wish came true?
願いが かなったんだね
Yeah...
You should go home before it gets dark.
暗くなる前に帰ったほうがいいよ
Right... I'll go home after the
cicadas stop chirping.
うん ヒグラシが鳴きやんだら帰るよ
Asuna...
アスナ
I'll give you a blessing.
祝福をあげる
Close your eyes.
目をつむって
Okay...
W-Was that a... k-k-k-kiss?
い… 今
あの… キ キ…
キ… キス
Asuna.
アスナ
All I wish is for you to live.
ただ 君に生きていてほしい
That's all I want...
それだけでいいんだ
U-Um, uh...
あ… あの… えっと
Sorry, see you tomorrow!
ごめん また明日
Tomorrow, then.
また明日
Whoa, what a shock...
びっくりしたな
Shun...
シュン… くん
So, it was her that heard my final song...
あの子だったんだ
最後の唄を聴いてくれていたのは
She called you Mimi, right?
ミミって言うんだね お前は
Please, lead Asuna to
a better place in my stead.
僕の代わりにどうかアスナを 良き場所に導いてあげてほしい
At this point,
the fear is almost unbearable...
今になって たまらなく怖いんだ
But at the same time, there's just as
powerful happiness.
でも 同じくらい幸せでもある
It's like my hand can almost reach them...
手が 届きそうだ
I'm home, Asuna.
ただいま アスナ
Welcome home! You must be
tired from the night shift.
おかえりなさい 夜勤 お疲れさま
うん あら お弁当２つ？
Yeah... Oh, two lunches today?
Yeah, one's for a friend!
うん 友達の分
Mom, you'll eat breakfast, right?
お母さん朝ごはん食べるでしよ？
Yeah.
Maybe we could eat it together?
私も一緒に食べてこうかな
何言ってるの もう食べたんでしよ？
What are you talking about?
You've eaten already, right?
I can still eat a bit more. Actually,
I'm still kind of hungry.
もう一杯くらい食べられるよ まだ ちよっと お腹すいてるし
No. You have to make sure
you're not late to school.
夕メよ ちゃんと遅れないように学校行きなさい
Asuna, why don't we go out to
dinner somewhere tonight?
アスナ 今晩どっか 夕食食べに行こうか
私 一日休みだから
I have the day off, you see.
Really?
ホント？じゃ 6時までには帰ってくるから
Then I'll be home before six!
Six?
6時？
Today's Saturday, right?
Where are you going?
今日 土曜日でしよ？ どこ行くの？
友達のとこ いってきまーす
To a friend's place! See you later!
あっ ねえ あなた スカーフは？
Hey, what happened to your scarf?
なくしちゃったの 購買で買う
I lost it. I'll buy another
at the school store!
Have a nice day!
いってらっしゃーい
A friend, huh?
友達か…
Are you sure about that?
それは確かなんでしようか？ ええ そうです はい　はい
Ah, I see. Yes, yes...
Anyway, I'll ask tomorrow.
とにかく 明日お伺いします
And I told him I'd come today...
また明日って言ったのにな
Maybe it's because of the rain?
雨だからかな
I'm home.
ただいま一
Sorry, Mom... can you get me a towel?
お母さん ごめん タオルもらえる？
My, look at you... you're sopping wet!
まあ あなた びしょ濡れじゃない
You didn't bring an umbrella?
傘 持ってなかったの？
No... H-Hey, I can dry myself!
えっちょっと… 自分で拭けるよ
Mom?
お…お…お母さん？
え…何？
What is it?
The body of a boy with your scarf
wrapped around his arm
あなたのスカーフを 腕にまいた男の子の体が
was found in the Shimonofuchi riverbed.
下ノ淵の河原で見つかったの
Asuna... That boy died.
アスナ その子は…亡くなったのよ
That's got to be someone else...
それは…人違いだよ
After all, it's not like he fell or anything.
だって落ちたりしないもの
Asuna...
アスナ
I'm fine. I'm sure it's a mistake,
don't worry.
大丈夫 違うもん 心配しないで
あっ 雨だし… 外食 また今度にしない？
Since it's raining,
let's do dinner some other time.
I need to do my homework.
私 宿題やっちゃうね
Asuna...
アスナ
大丈夫だって
I'm fine, okay?
Shun!
シュンくん
シュンく—ん
Dad's not coming back anymore?
お父さん もう戻ってこない？
Is he, Mom?
ねえ お母さん
To wish for something like that...
I'm sure he wouldn't want that, yes...
それを願うのは きっと いけないことなんでしょうね
死ぬことは生きることの一部だと お父さんは言ってたから
Dad said that death was
a part of life, after all.
Even so...
でも…
I...
私は…
And in that way, his wife died.
そのようにして 彼の妻は死んでしまった
Overcome with grief,
悲しみに暮れたイザナギは
Izanagi decided to travel to the land
of Yomi far underneath the earth,
地の底にある黄泉の国へと 降りることを決意した
in order to bring his dead wife,
Izanami, back from the dead.
死んでしまった妻 イザナミを生き返らせるために
After traveling deep underneath the earth,
深い地の底でついに再会した夫に 妻はこう言う
they finally reunited, and she said:
"I have already become a resident
of the land of the dead."
「私は既に死者の国の住人と なってしまいました」
"However, if the god of Yomi allows it,
I can return home with you."
「でも黄泉の神の許しがあれば　あなたの元に帰ることができる」
"But for that to happen,
there is one condition."
「そのためには ーつだけ条件があります」
"While I am talking with the god,
you must not look at my body."
「私が神と話をしている間」
「決して 私の姿を見ないでください」と
しかしイサナギは その約束を破ってしまう
But Izanagi broke that promise.
He opened the gate to Yomi.
黄泉の扉を開けてしまったのだ
妻はついに イザナギの元へは戻らない
And therefore Izanagi's wife can
no longer return with him.
That's from the first verse of
the Kojiki Mythology.
「古事記」に描かれた神話の一節です
Similar myths of people heading below
the earth to resurrect people
恋人をよみがえらせるために 地下に赴くという同型の神話や伝説は
are found throughout the world.
世界中に散見されます
The land of Yomi.
黄泉の国　冥府
Underworld, Hades, Shambhala, Agartha...
ハデス シャンバラ アかレタ
They are called different names,
呼び方は異なりますが すべて地下世界の存在を伝えています
but they are all said to be worlds
underneath the earth.
People once believed that the land of
Yomi held the secret to death itself.
かつて人は
地下にこそ 人間の死の秘密があると考えたのです
Everyone, it is time to go home from school.
皆さん 下校の時刻となりました
Is there something about Asuna?
アスナさんが どうかしましたか
Those students still in the building,
please turn off the lights,
No, she just seems very serious, so I was
wondering what kind of student she was...
いえ ずいぶん熱心だったので どんな生徒なのかと
close the windows, and be mindful
of cars on your way home.
Yes... She's well behaved,
and a very good girl.
そうね おとなし＜て とてもいい子ですよ
But her father passed away
when she was young,
Mythology section
でもお父さまは 早くに亡くなられているし
お母さまは看護婦をして お忙しいみたいだし
and her mother seems to be very
busy with her nursing work.
聞き分けがいい分 ずいぶん無理してるんじゃないかしら
I do wonder if she's trying too
hard to be good, you know...
Is that so?
そうですか
And they found that corpse of the
unidentified boy before, yes?
それに以前 身元不明の少年の遺体ガ 見つかったことがあったでしよ
Asuna, aren't you going home?
アスナちゃん 帰るの？
Yuu... I have something
I'd like to ask Mr. Morisaki.
ユウちゃん
私 ちょっと モリサキ先生に 聞きたいことがあるの
I don't really like him so much...
私 あの先生 ちよっと苦手 今日の授業もなんか怖くて
Today's lesson was kinda scary...
怖い？
Scary?
I heard a rumor that his wife died...
ウワサなんだけど　先生の奥さん 死んじゃってるんだって
Pardon me.
失礼します
So?
どうだった？
Seems like he went home already.
もう帰っちゃったって
じゃあね
Later!
また明日ね
See you tomorrow.
You're...
君は…
Um, I'm sorry, but I had something
I wanted to ask you.
あのすみません
私 先生にお聞きしたいことがあって
Wait here just a moment.
ちょっと待っていて＜れるか
Do you drink coffee?
コーヒー飲めるかい？
あ ハイ ミルク入れていただければ
Yes! lf you could put some milk in it...
ありがとうございます
Thank you.
Um, I'm sorry for barging in like this.
あの… 急にお邪魔しちゃって すみません
池田先生からお住まいを聞いて
I asked Ms. Ikeda where you lived.
見てのとおり  一人暮らしだ 遠慮は要らないよ
As you can see, I live by myself.
Make yourself at home.
Of course, I've just arrived here...
All I really have are books.
越してきて  間もないものでね 本ぐらいしかないのだが
So, what is it?
それで  どうしたんだい？
U-Um, about class today...
あ あの…
今日の授業のことで
You were listening very intently, yes?
君は ずいぶん熱心に聞いていたね
You have someone you want
to bring back from the dead?
生き返らせたい人でもいるのかな
So, it was you who met the boy
that came from Agartha...
アガルタから来た少年に 会ったというのは君か
Look at this.
これを見なさい
We call them "Quetzal Coatl".
我々は それを  ケツァルトルと呼んでいる
They are the gatekeepers that guard
the entrances to Agartha.
アガルタへの入り□を守る門番だよ
And what do you think of this one?
もう一つ これをどう思う？
さっきのと ちょっと似てます
It looks similar to the one from before.
It's a 3,000 year old statue
of a god from Sumeria.
3千年前のシュメリアの 古い神の像だ
Once, there were gods like
this all around the world,
かつて世界には あらゆる場所に このような神がいて
guiding the path of
the yet young humanity.
まだ幼かった人類を導いていた
Those are the Quetzal Coatl.
それガケツァルトルだ
Eventually humanity grew up, and the existence
of gods was no longer necessary.
やがて人類は成長し 神マの存在は不要になり
The Quetzal Coatl, realizing
their role had now ended,
役割を終えたことを悟った ケツァルトルたちは門番を残して地下に潜った
hid themselves under the
earth as gatekeepers.
いくつかの氏族を従えてね
Along with a number of different clans.
シゾク？
Clans?
A small number of humans went with the
Quetzal Coatl underneath the ground.
少数の人間がケツァルトルと共に 地下に降りたということだ
In other words, to the underworld, Agartha.
それガ地下世界アガルタだ
In Agartha remain the gods that disappeared,
and knowledge yet unknown,
アがレタには 失われた神々の英知がいまだ残され
あらゆる願いがかなう場所が あると言う
and it is said to be a place where wishes can be fulfilled.
死者の復活さえも
Even resurrecting the dead!
Is Agartha real?
アガルタって本当に？
Who knows? Perhaps it is just a legend.
さあ ただの伝説かもしれない
All I have been doing is researching
all the different theories.
さまざまな説はあるが 私はただ研究しているだけだからね
But...
でも…
You should head home. It's getting dark.
もう帰りなさい 暗くなってレまう
ありがとうございました
Thank you.
I'm not sure I was much help...
あまり役には立てなかったかな
No, you were... Um...
いえ あの…
Mr. Morisaki, I'm sure that
Agartha really exists.
先生 私はアガル夕って きっとあると思います
It'll be night soon. Go straight home,
and don't stray from the path.
すぐ夜になる
寄り道せずに まっすぐ家に帰りなさい
Mimi?
Hey, wait... Mimi!
ねえ ちょっと ミミ
Wait, I said!
待ってよ
Mimi, where are you?
ミミ どこ？
Shun, Shun!
シュンくん  シュンくん
I knew it!
やっぱり
Who are you?
誰だ お前
Did he make contact with a Topsider?
あいつ地上人と接触したのか
Shun...?
シュンくん？
He's gone.
Just forget everything that's happened.
あいつはもういない 起きたことはすべて忘れろ
Arch Angel? I have to go!
アルカンジェリか
俺はもう行く
A boy from Agartha? Hand over the clavis.
アかレタの少年か クラヴィスを渡してもらおう
Who are these people?
何？この人たち
Damn it!
クソ
Don't hit them.
当てるなよ
We'll let them lead us to it.
このまま追い責めで案内させる
That jewel...
その宝石…
This clavis?
I came to the surface to get it back.
クラヴィスか？
俺は これを取り戻しに 地上に来たんだ
This way, they can't get in.
これでヤツらは入ってこれない 朝を待って家に帰れ
Wait until morning and then go home.
The surface?
地上って　やっぱり アガルタは地下にあるの？
So Agartha really is underground?
You've even heard about that?
そんなことまで聞いてるのか
Shun... Could you have lost your memories?
シュンくん  もしかして記憶喪失？
Now see here...
あのなあ…
In there.
この中だ
Damn it! They're coming in!
クソヤツら 入ってくるぞ
Hey, how far are we...
ねえ 一体どこまで…
Hurry up and follow!
They're coming after us!
早く来い 追いつかれるぞ
Shun, is this cave...
シュンくん この洞窟って
I told you already! I'm not Shun!
言っただろ  俺はシュンじゃない
I'm under no obligation
to save you, you know.
本当は お前を助ける 義理だってないんだ
Then what's the deal?
If you're not Shun, then who are you?
どうしちゃったの？シュンくんじゃなきゃ 誰なのよ
Quiet. You stay here.
静かに
お前はここにいろ
何？
What?
The gatekeeper.
門番だ
The gatekeepers once guided
humans long ago.
門番ってのは  ずっと昔人間の導き手だったんだ
But because of the polluted
atmosphere above,
でも地上の汚れた大気のせいで　今では  ほとんど心を失っている
most of them have lost their senses...
It'd be great if they remembered...
思い出してくれればいいが
Shun!
シュンくん
Stay there!
そこにいろ
Are you okay?
大丈夫？
まだ終わりじゃない  クラヴィスを持っててくれ
It's not over yet. Take the clavis.
I don't want to kill the gatekeeper.
殺したくないんだ　何とか眠らせる
I have to put him to sleep!
Shun!
シュンくん　シュンくん
If there's a Quetzal Coatl, then
this must be the entrance!
ケツァルトルがいるとは…
やはり ここが入り口だ
大丈夫？逃げよう
Are you okay?
Let's run...
This is a Pakicetus... They were
supposed to be extinct.
こいつは絶滅したはずの バキケトゥスか
What is it?
何です？
An ancient whale from
50 million years ago. Kill it.
5千万年前の太古のクジラだ 殺せ
But we have to recover all the evidence...
しかし 徴はすべて回収しろと
As long as we get that clavis, there
won't be any complaints.
クラヴィスが手に入れば 文句は出まい
Do it.
やれ
Stop!
やめろ
Come here with that clavis!
クラヴィスを持ったまま こちらに来い
If you don't, I'll kill the boy.
さもなくば 少年を殺す
Don't do it.
行くな
I could just kill both of you.
ここで2人とも殺すこともできる
Shun...
シュンくん
I'll save you when I see a chance.
隙を見て助ける
Right.
Come, and don't stop halfway.
止まらずに来い
Watch over the boy here.
ここで少年を見張れ
Is that the gate?
あれが扉ですか
Most likely.
南極の例では 爆薬も削岩機も効かなかったそうだ
おそらくな
Neither explosives nor drills will be
effective, like at the South Pole.
Touch the clavis to that light.
クラヴィスで その光に触れてみろ
What's the matter? Do it.
どうした やりなさい
The Interstitial Sea...
狭間の海だ
Finally, it's within my grasp...
ついに手が届く
Good work, men.
同行 ご苦労
Commander, what are you...
中佐　何を…
I'll be going alone from here.
ここからは私一人で行く
Give the old men back at
Europa my best wishes.
ェウロパの老人たちに よろしく伝えてくれ
動くな
Don't move!
Shun!
シュンくん
What's the meaning of this?
どういうつもりだ
Mr. Morisaki?
モリサキ先生
Now that I've come this far, I have
no reason to be your enemy.
ここまで来た以上 君と敵対する理由はない
All I want to do is go to Agartha.
私はアガルタに行きたいだけだ
Agartha is falling into ruin.
アガルタは滅びゆく場所だ
Nothing Arch Angel hopes to find is there.
お前たち アルカンジェリが 期待するようなものは何もない
I do not seek the secret to eternal life
or the knowledge of the ancients.
私が欲しいのは不死の秘密でも 古代の英知でもない
All I want is to return
my wife to the living.
ただ 妻を生き返らせたいだけだ
Do as you wish, I don't care.
どうしようと勝手にしろ
My only mission was to retrieve the clavis.
俺の役目は クラヴィスの回収だけだ
What's your name?
お前 各前は？
Asuna.
アスナ
I'm Shin. Shun's younger brother.
俺はシン シュンの弟だ
Shin? Then, Shun is...
シン？
じゃあ シュンくんは？
My brother is dead.
兄は死んだ
He knew that he couldn't survive
on the surface for long,
地上では 長くは生きられないことを覚悟で淀を破って外に出たんだ
yet he broke the rules and went anyway.
I'm leaving now.
俺は もう行く
You can open the exit even without a clavis.
出口はクラヴィスなしでも開く
I'm sorry about you getting involved,
Asuna...
巻き込んで悪かったな
アスナ
Shin...
シン
I've put you in a scary situation.
君には怖い思いをさせたな
Mr. Morisaki, why?
モリサキ先生 どうして…
Have you heard of the name Arch Angel?
アルカンジェリという名前を 知っているか？
No...
いえ
It's the only organization that recognizes
the existence of Agartha.
アカルタの存在を把握している 唯一の組織で
It wants the knowledge of the underworld
in order to lead humanity on the proper path.
地下世界の英知を得て 人類を良き方向に導こうとしている
I am a member, and have been searching
for the entrance to Agartha for ten years.
私は そこの一員で10年間 アガルタへの入り口を探していた
But, the people you were with...
でも 一緒にいた人たちは
Arch Angel is actually just a group
of empty headed Gnostics.
アルカンジェリの実際は 空疎なグノーシス主義者の集まりだ
I have no interest in such things.
神や世界の真理に 私は興味はない
My only goal is resurrecting my wife.
目的は妻を よみがえらせることだけだ
I'm now going to head to Agartha,
and search for a way.
私は このままアカルタに行き その方法を探す
Sorry for putting you in such danger.
危険な目に遭わせて すまなかったな
I knew it... It's vita aqua.
やはりヴィータクアだ
Mr. Morisaki!
先生
Mr. Morisaki...
先生私も行きます
I'm coming too!
Why? Do you want to bring
that dead boy back to life?
なぜ？ 死んだ少年を生き返らせたいのか
Well...
それは…分かりませんけど…
I don't really know...
But!
でも
It may be a dangerous journey, and
I don't know when we'll be able to return.
危険な旅になるかもしれないし いつ戻れるかも分からない
I understand.
はい
Come.
来なさい
This is an ancient fluid known as vita aqua.
これはヴィータクアという 太古の液体だ
It is hardly buoyant at all, so if it fills your
lungs, you should be able to breathe.
浮力がほとんどなく 肺を満たせば呼吸までもできる
Agartha is below.
アガル夕は この底にある
Um, Mr. Morisaki, wait...
先生 ちょっと待って
It's okay. You can breathe in the water.
大丈夫だ 水を飲めば息ができる
This is to bring back someone precious...
大切なものを取り戻すためだ
Make your decision, Asuna!
覚悟を決めなさい アスナ
We'll be able to meet her soon...
もうすぐ会えるな
Yes... I pray that this child's
life will be a blessing...
そうね この子の人生が 祝福と共にあることを願うわ
Don't worry. Just by being born,
life is already full of happiness.
大丈夫
生まれ落ちるというだけで  命はもう十分に幸せだよ
That's right...
あ…そうだ
I need to be born soon.
私 そろそう生まれなくちゃ
Stars...
星…
Mimi...
Are you awake?
目が覚めたか
That little guy popped out of your bag.
そいつは君のリュックから 出てきたんだ
君が連れてきたのか？
You brought it with you?
No...
いえ
When did you...
あんた いつの間に
You might not have the luxury to
take it with you the whole way.
最後まで連れていく余裕は ないかもしれんぞ
With me?
連れて…
Mr. Morisaki, is this...
先生 ここって…
It looks like we can get through those
stairs on the other side. Let's go.
向こうの階段は通れそうだ 行こう
Something is here.
何かいます
Yes...
This might be a gatekeeper, a Quetzal Coatl.
おそらく門番… ケツァルトルだ
It's looking at us.
こっちを見てる
I guess we'll have to take it straight on.
正面から行くしかないな
Mimi!
Mimi, come here.
ミミ おいで
Asuna!
アスナ
Mimi!
Asuna, let's go.
アスナ
行くぞ
That might be more useful than I thought.
存外 役に立つかもしれんな
Agartha.
アガルタ
Mr. Morisaki, look!
先生 あれ
Shakuna Vimana! The ark
on which rides God itself!
シャクナ·ヴィマーナ  神が乗ると言われてる舟だ
It's just as the literature said...
文献のとおりだ
God...
神様…
That's...
それは
A clavis?
クラヴィス？
A fragment of one?
But why do you have that?
欠片か？なぜ君が？
It's a crystal for a radio. I was told
it was a memento of my dad.
ラジオの鉱石なんです  お父さんの形見だって
A memento?
形見？
Clavis is Latin for "key".
クラヴィスとはラティン語で 　鍵という意味だ
It may end up being of help to us later.
今後 我々の助けになるかもしれない　大切に持っておきなさい
Take good care of it.
Right.
はい
Let's head in the same direction as that ark.
あの舟の向かう方向に行こう
Something should be there... Something
we are looking for.
何かがあるはずだ  私たちの求めるものが
どうぞ
Here.
There are traces of villages,
just as you thought!
やっぱり村の跡があります
どこまで行っても廃虚だけだな
Although no matter where we go,
they're in ruins.
There might still be some vegetable
fields. I'll go check.
畑が残ってるかも  私 見てきます
Come here, Mimi!
おいで ミミ
Toward Finis Terra...
The Gate of Life and Death...
フィニス　テラの向こう
生死の門か
Mr. Morisaki, look!
先生 見て
Looks like I've found tonight's dinner...
今夜は ごちそうかも
See?
ほら
Some potatoes might be poisonous,
so just in case...
芋類なら毒があるかもしれない  念のため…
水で毒抜きします
I'll remove the poison with water!
And also, your clothes...
それから その服
Yours are pretty dirty too, you know.
先生のも だいぶ汚れてますよ
I'll wash them afterwards,
so please get changed.
あとで洗うので  着替えといてください
Potatoes, yay!
お芋だぁ
These are good.
うまいな
Thank goodness there was still
some salt left in the kitchen.
よかった  台所に お塩も少し残ってたんです
I'm surprised.
意外だったな
Is this journey fun for you?
君はこの旅が楽しいのか？
I...
私…一人でラジオを聴きながら
Whenever I listened to the radio,
どこか遠い 違う場所に行かなきゃって  ずっと思ってたんです
I felt like there was a far off
world I had to get to.
"This is not where I belong. There is
a place I've never seen before..."
私がいたい場所はここじゃない  見たこともないどこかなんだって
Then I met a mysterious boy, and
chased him all the way here...
そしたら不思議な男の子と出会って  その人を追って ここまで来て
Ever since I came to Agartha, my heart
has been racing for some reason...
アガルタに来てから私 何だか…
ずっとドキドキしてるんです
That's why I'm sure that ahead
of here, something...
だから この先に何か… きっと
Um...
あの…
Not being able to see the stars at night
makes me somewhat uneasy...
星が見えない夜というのは  何か不安なものだな
It makes you realize just how
solitary human existence is.
人間がどれほど孤独な存在なのかを思い知らされてしまう
Shin Canaan Praeses.
シン·クァーナン·プラェセス
As for the recovery of the clavis,
we laud your service.
クラヴィスの回収  まずは大儀であった
But you have made a grave error.
だが そなたは過ちを犯した
A man and girl have come from
the surface with clavis in hand,
地上から来た男と少女が
クラヴィスを手に  生死の門を目指しておる
making pace toward the Gate
of Life and Death.
What? But I have the clavis right here...
しかし クラヴィスはここに
Theirs is a different fragment.
別の欠片を持っていたのだ
You stood there and foolishly allowed those
Topsiders entrance into Agartha...
そなたは地上人を みすみすアガルタに招いてしまった
This was a grave error.
大きな過ちじゃ
But the task which I was given was only...
でも 俺のいただいた役目は
Out with such excuses!
Don't you understand?
疎明は要らぬ　皆まで言わねば分からぬか
Our days of prosperity are long past, and
we are living the long days of twilight.
かつての繁栄は もはや遠く　我々は今や永い黄昏を生きている
Our wish now is to fade away into
Astral, the endpoint of life itself.
このまま生命の終点たるアストラムに  溶けゆくのが我らの望み
But every time a gate is opened,
しかし ひとたび門が開かれれば　地上人は再びアガルタに押し迫り
Topsiders come and press in upon Agartha,
throwing our peaceful existence into turmoil...
平穏は混濁の中に  のみ込まれるだろう
We shan't ever forget the suffering we once
endured, be it even for a moment.
かつて我々が受けた苦しみ
生半に忘れることはできぬ
Such a pity.
嘆かわしいことじゃ
Facing the coming of age ceremony,
your eyes are as of yet not open.
成人の儀を前にして  そなたの眼は いまだ開かれておらぬ
Unable to peer into the vision
of the Quetzal Coatl...
ケツァルトルの視界を  のぞ＜こともできず
Unsuited to sense the breath of the clavis!
クラヴィスの息ざしを  感じることも かなわず
Your brother had natural gifts.
そなたの兄には天分があったのだが
But his soul was weak, and his yearning
for the surface grew ever stronger.
宿業の病ガ地上へのあこがれを 強めてしまった
シン·クァーナン·プラ工セス
Shin Canaan Preases,
I give you a new task.
そなたに新たな使命を与える
Shin!
シン
Seri! Aren't you in the middle of a task?
セリ お役目中だろ
Just a short break isn't a problem.
ちよっとぐらい大丈夫
Seri, about Shun...
セリ シュンのことは…
I know.
知ってる
It's a shame.
残念だった
No... Even if the illness was hastened,
I'm sure that Shun saw what he wanted to.
ううん たとえ 病を早めてでも　シュンは きっと見たいものを見れたんだもの
シン
Shin... You have another task, yes?
またお役目を もらったんでしよ？
Yes. I have to find the Topsiders
and confiscate their clavis.
ああ 地上人を捜して クラヴィスを奪取する
But that's...
でも それって
It's not like I was told I had to kill them.
But if I have to...
殺せと言われたわけじゃないさ  でも必要となれば…
How awful, making you do such
a dangerous task all by yourself!
そんな危険な お役目に シン 一人きりなんて
After our parents died, the people
of the village raised us.
親が死んでから 村は俺たち兄弟を育ててくれた
I have to repay that debt.
その恩は返さなくちゃ
Eat.
食べなさい
ありがとうございます
Thank you very much...
Maybe we should make some soup?
スープも作るか
Here.
ほら
What is it?
どうした？
You seem to be getting along
all of a sudden.
いつの間にか仲いいんですね
Well, if it comes down to it,
we can use the cat for food.
ああ いざとなったら 猫は食料になるからな
冗談だ
I'm joking.
Mr. Morisaki... It's like you're my... dad.
先生って
お父さん
…みたい
Don't be silly.
バカなことを言うな
How rare for you to get a fever.
珍しいわね  あなたが熱を出すなんて
I thought it was my job
to fall ill all the time.
倒れるのは  いつもは私の役目なのに
I'm sorry.
すまない
If you feel that way, can you
promise me something?
そう思ってるなら 一つ約束してくれる？
What?
何？
Even when I'm gone, promise me
you'll keep on living a good life.
私がいなくなってからも ちゃんとしっかり生きていくって
Lisa, my next mission will be over soon.
リサ　次の任務は すぐに終わるよ
After I get back, let's go back
to my country together.
帰ってきたら  一緒に僕の国に行こう
If we do that, your illness will-
そうすれば君の病気も…
That's not what I asked.
そういうことじゃないの
Listen... All people pass on sometime.
ねえ 人は誰でも  いつか必ずいなくなるものなの
The only difference is whether
it comes sooner, or later.
違いは それが遅いか早いかだけ
And I'm just going a bit before you...
そして私は あなたより それがちょっとだけ早いの
There's no changing that.
それは もう決まっていることなのよ
Lisa...
リサ
Don't say that.
そんなことはないよ
You aren't going to leave me,
and I am never going to leave your side.
君はいなくならないし　僕も君の前から  いなくなったりはしない
I would never prepare for your absence...
僕は…
僕は君の不在に 備えたりはしない　決して
For certain...
Lisa, are you there?
リサ そこにいたのか
Um... Mr. Morisaki, you seemed like
you were uncomfortable, so I...
あの… 先生 苦しそうだったから
Asuna... Did I say something?
アスナ
私は何か言ったか？
No...
いえ
A rainbow.
虹だ
They're heading to where the Izoku dwell.
夷族の土地のほうに向かってる
I must hurry!
急ごう
Got it!
あっ入った
I see...
そっか
So the scenery that I would see while listening
to the radio was part of Agartha...
私がラジオを聴きながら 見ていた景色はアガルタだったんだね
Let's go, Asuna. On a journey to know
what it means to say goodbye.
行こう アスナ
さよならを知るための旅だ
It's okay, don't cry. You're all right.
大丈夫 泣かないで
大丈夫
Any luck?
どう？
What should we do?
どうしよう
What's wrong?
何? どうしたの？
They're gone.
いない
I see the clavis!
見えたクラヴィスだ
They can't go out from the shadows!
あ… 影から出られないんだ
Come here!
ねえ来て
It's okay, come here!
大丈夫 おいで
Climb!
登って
お願い 頑張って
Please, you can do it!
Grab on!
つかまれ
Asuna!
アスナ
Come!
来い
You're... Shin?
あなた シン？
Looks like you got it right this time.
今度は間違えなかったな
This is a nest of Izoku.
ここは夷族の巣だ
They will devour you and your
so called defiled blood.
ヤツら お前たちを ケガレタ血だと言って喰い殺したがってる
逃げるぞ
We're getting out of here!
Shin! How did you know we were here?
シン
どうして ここが 分かったの？
Um, after we last met, I chased
after you into Agartha!
私 あの後  シンを追ってアガルタまで…
And that's caused me a whole
lot of trouble, thank you!
こっちは いい迷惑だぜ
What? I just wanted to see you again...
何よ 私はシンに もう一度…
無駄口 言わずに走れ ヤツら 追ってくるぞ
Don't talk, just run!
They're coming after you!
I am running!
走ってるよ
シン シン 追ってきたよ
Shin! Shin, they're coming!
Asuna, jump!
アスナ 跳べ
Shin!
シン
You okay?
平気？
Let's go!
行くぞ
Asuna, you have a fragment
of a clavis, right?
アスナ クラヴィスの欠片を 持ってるな
Yeah...
You should hand it over to me.
渡してもらうからな
Shin!
シン
I have to save him.
助けなくちゃ
Hold it, little guy!
おい チビ
Asuna!
アスナ
Hey, Asuna!
アスナおい
Asuna...
アスナ…
A horse?
馬？
He told you to give him the clavis?
クラヴィスを渡せと
彼がそう言ったのか？
It doesn't seem like those things
君たちをさらった連中といい  我々は歓迎されざる存在のようだな
were planning to give us a nice welcome.
And what'll we do with her?
この子も どうするか
What is it?
どうしたの？
Something's over there?
あっちに何かあるの？
川下か…
Downstream?
Shin!
あ…シン
すごい汗
You're covered in sweat!
Asuna?
アスナ
Shin!
シン
You're safe, too?
お前も無事か？
よかった 気がついて
Thank goodness. You're conscious...
Ah, right... We were swept away...
そうか 俺たち流されて…
Wait, I'll get you water.
待って 今 水を
You!
あっ お前は
You're from Arch Angel!
アルカンジェリ
I know you have a clavis.
Leave it here and get out of Agartha!
クラヴィスを持っているはずだ
それを置いてアガルタを去れ
Why?
なぜ
How should I know?
This is what I've been tasked with!
理由など知るか それガ俺の役目だ
Hand over the clavis!
クラヴィスを渡せ
Let's go where she pointed.
あの子の指レた方向に行ってみよう  集落があるのかもしれない
There might be a village there.
I'm bringing him with us.
この人も連れていきます
Do as you wish.
好きにしなさい
人がいる…
There are people here!
The first living village.
初めての生きた村だな
Let's go, but watch yourself.
用心して行こう
Dear...
あ… あんた…
It couldn't be...
まさか…
They're Topsiders.
地上人だそうだ
Really?
本当か？
不吉な…
A bad omen...
I hope everything's okay...
大丈夫かしら
Everyone, stand back!
皆 下がりなさい
It's the defiled child that was kidnapped.
おととい さらわれたケガレゴです
The one who can no longer speak
after her mother passed away.
母親ガ死んでから  言葉を失くしたとか
Halt!
止まれ
Dinah's child, yes?
ディナの子か
She sure has grown.
大きくなったな
Thank you for bringing
our village's child back.
村の子を届けてくれたこと  礼を申し上げる
But you are Topsiders from the surface.
だが そなたたちは地上人であろう
Our village of Amaurot
cannot accept Topsiders.
アモロートの村は地上人を  受け入れることはできぬ
どうか お帰り願おう
Please turn back.
U-Um, could you at least take
a look at this person?
あっ あの… せめて
この人だけでも  診ていただけませんか
Those clothes... He's from Canaan?
あの服 カナンの出か
He's injured, and he has a fever.
ケガ人なんです  熱があって
Why is someone of Agartha with
those from the surface?
なぜアガルタ人が地上の者と
ならぬ
I cannot.
Begone!
去れ
Wait!
待て
Manna, I'm so happy you've come back!
マナ よく戻った
Please, forgive my village's rudeness.
村の非礼を許してほしい
Not a word of thanks for saving
my granddaughter, eh?
孫を救ってくれた礼を   させてはもらえぬか
ご宿老
Old Master!
Just for one eve... Must I suffer
the dishonor of not even doing that much?
一夜かぎりじゃ   わしの顔を立ててはくれんか
This way.
こっちじゃ
Bringing you through the village would
cause you to stand out too much.
村の中を通るには   そなたたちは目立ちすぎる
His fever will break soon.
じき 熱は下がろう
Although it will be a little while before
he is able to move again.
動けるようになるには   今しばらく かかるだろうが
He'll live, so there is no need for worry.
死にはしない あまり心配なさるな
Thank goodness.
よかった
This is all thanks to you...
おじいさんのおかげです
That was a wound from the Izoku, yes?
夷族にやられた傷じゃな
Izoku?
イゾク？
They hate both light and water...
They're a cursed tribe.
光と水を嫌う 呪われた種族じゃ
But they are part of the structure that maintains
this world in its current state.
だが 今ある姿を保とうとする  世界の仕組みのーつでもある
That is why they hate it so when the
two sides are mixed together.
だからヤツらは  モノの交わりを憎むのだ
Mixed together?
モノの交わり？
So, that child...
では あの子は？
Manna's father is a Topsider.
マナは父親が地上人じゃ
Things such as that happen not oft.
そういうことも まれには起きる
Get out of our village!
この村から出ていけ
Get out!
I apologize, Miss...
すまんの お嬢さん
But the coming of Topsiders is not
looked upon as a good omen to us.
しかし 地上人の来訪は  我々にとって良い兆しではないのだ
Asuna.
アスナ
In the past, kings and
emperors from the surface
かつて地上の王や皇帝たちは
数百年にわたり アガル夕から  富や技を奪い続けてきた
came to steal the wealth and wisdom
of Agartha for hundreds of years.
The kings needed Agartha's
knowledge and treasure
王たちが地上を支配するためにはアガルタの知識や財宝ガ  必要だったからじゃ
to rule over the surface, you see.
And what they brought in return
were countless wars...
その代わりに彼らが持ち込んだのは  数知れぬ争いじゃった
We were more glorious than
anywhere on the surface.
地上のどこよりも壮麗だった都市はすべて滅び
But our cities were all destroyed,
and our birth rate dwindled.
生まれる子も次第に減り　今や いくつかの村が残るのみ
Now there are but a handful
of villages that remain.
And so we shut the gates with the clavises,
だから我々は  クラヴィスによって扉を閉じ
locking them to prevent anyone
from the surface from entering.
地上からは入れぬよう  鍵をかけたのじゃ
I'll show you to my archive.
御仁は書庫に案内しよう
Will you help me prepare dinner there, miss?
お嬢さんは そちらで   夕食の準備を手伝ってもらえるかな
Yes.
はい
This way.
こっちじゃ
Mimi...
Manna...
マナ…
What next, Elder?
おじいさん 次は？
では そこの大根を切ってくれんかの
Would you cut up that bigroot for me?
はい
Sure.
You mean this?
これですね？
Yes...
A daikon...
ダイコンだ…
こら ミミ
Hey, Mimi!
I've never seen a Yadoriko get along
so well with a Topsider before.
ヤドリコが地上人に  これほど懐くのを見たのは初めてじゃよ
ヤドリコ？猫のことですか？
Yadoriko? You mean a cat?
Animals in which reside God's children.
神の子が宿った動物のことじゃ
Raised along with humans,
after they serve their purpose,
人と共に育ち 役目を果たした後は
ケツァルトルの一部となり  いつまでも生き続ける
they become one with the Quetzal Coatl
and live on for eternity.
God...
神様？
Isn't it nice to be mistaken for such a
wonderful creature like that, Mimi?
よかったね ミミ  そんな立派な動物と間違えてもらえて
Now then, would you give Manna
a bath before dinner is ready?
さて
できあがるまでに  マナを風呂に入れてくれるかな
A bath?!
お…お風呂?
Baths sure are amazing...
お風呂ってすごいね
Hey Manna, hold it!
こらマナ 待ちなさい
Mr. Morisaki...
先生
How do you like this outfit?
どうですか？この格好 おじいさんに借りたんです
I borrowed it from the Elder.
It doesn't suit you.
似合ってはいないな
Don't cry while you eat.
泣かずに食べなさい
But it's so good!
だって おいしくて
Elder, I was wondering if you could
answer my question from earlier.
ご老人
私の先ほどの質問に   答えてはいただけないだろうか
It is forbidden to bring back
the dead here in Agartha.
アガルタでは死者の復活は  禁じられている
If it is forbidden, that means there is a way.
禁じられるということは できるということです
Life and death are just part of the
flow of something much bigger.
御仁
生も死も　もっと大きな  ものの流れの一部でしかない
Those humans who wish to interrupt
that flow shall not be permitted.
その流れを遮るようなことは  人間には許されておらぬ
Permitted?
許し？
Why? Whose permission must I ask?
なぜ 誰に許しを乞うのです？
Elder, even we on the surface
know such platitudes.
ご老人 その程度の文言 至言など 地上にも溢れている
What I want to know is where and how
one can reunite with lost loved ones.
私が知りたいのは失った人間に  どこでどうやって再会できるのか
That's all.
それだけだ
Grieving over the dead is proper,
but to continue to pity them is erroneous.
死者を悼むのは正しいことだが　死者と己を哀れみ続けるのは  間違っている
You should not have involved a girl of such
youth in your own delusional fallacy.
自身の迷妄に 御仁は　年端もいかぬ少女を  巻き込むべきではなかった
Asuna came here of her own free will!
アスナが ここにいるのは アスナの意志だ
あの私…
Um! I...
All you do is sit here, staring up at the gods,
locked up in this cellar for 2,000 years!
ただ何かを仰ぎ見るだけ
あなたたちは そうやって　2干年も穴蔵に  閉じこもってきたのだ
Miss, I apologize,
but can you look after the boy?
お嬢さん すまないが  少年の様子を見てきてくれるかね
行っておいで
Go.
Okay.
はい
Those clothes...
その格好 似合ってないな
don't suit you at all.
That's not a nice thing to say!
何よその言い方
Why did you do it?
なぜ助けた？
Why did you save me?
なぜ俺を助けた
Because you saved me, too.
だってシンだって  私を助けてくれたじゃない
I was just forced to clean up after my brother.
俺は兄の尻ぬぐいを  させられているだけだ
Shun?
シュンくんの？
Shin!
シン
Don't force yourself...
まだ無理しちゃ…
You can't stay here.
お前たちは
ここにいちゃいけないんだ
Damn it...
I should have let the Izoku kill you,
then taken your clavis.
俺も… 夷族にお前を殺させてから  クラヴィスを奪うべきだった
No, I should have killed those
Arch Angels on the surface.
いや 地上でアルカンジェリともども  殺すべきだった
Leave.
出てってくれ
Shin?
シン…
I said leave!
出てけ
We'll leave early tomorrow.
明日は早く出発する  早めに寝ておきなさい
Get right to sleep.
I'm sorry.
I can't shelter Topsiders for long.
すまないね  地上人を長く匿うわけにはいかんのだ
I've said what I could to him.
わしに言えることは  あの御仁に伝えておいたよ
Tonight, at least,
sleep together with Manna.
今夜はせめて  マナと寝てやっておくれ
Mimi.
兄さん…
Brother...
Everyone set out on their journey
as a heartfelt cry for help.
皆懸命に  救いを求めて旅に出たのだ
If only somebody had been able to stop them...
誰に止めることができよう
Our time together made me feel like
my daughter had returned to me.
まるで娘が戻ってきたような 時間だったよ
Elder...
おじいさん…
Manna, take care!
マナ 元気で
The boat should get you across the
lake in two days and one night.
二昼夜ほどで  舟は湖に達するじゃろう
From there, you will be
near the place you seek.
そこから御仁らの目指す地は近い
You have my thanks for all that you've done.
何もかも感謝します
Asuna.
アスナ
Mimi, come here.
ミミ おいで
Hey, we're going...
ほら 行くんだよ
Mimi?
I think the little one has fulfilled its duty.
その子は自分の役目を 果たしたのかもしれんの
People cannot decide
what the Yadoriko do, see.
ヤドリコの行いを  人が決めることはできんのだよ
But...
そんな… ずっと一緒だったじゃない
I thought we'd always be together!
Mimi!
アスナ  どうやら受け入れるしかない
Asuna, you just have to accept it.
Elder, please...
ご老人 どうか頼みます
Mimi!
Mr. Morisaki, wait! I still...
先生 待って だって
Mimi!
Manna, take care of Mimi!
マナ ミミをお願い
Mimi, listen to what Manna says, okay?
ミミ マナの言うこと ちゃんと聞くんだよ
Farewell...
さよなら…
Mr. Morisaki...
先生
Do you remember what you said in class?
いつか授業でしてくださった話  覚えてますか？
About the myth of Izanagi and lzanami?
イザナギとイザナミの神話
Yes...
I was curious about the end,
so I read the rest in the library.
私最後が気になって  図書館で続きを読んだんです
What Izanagi saw at the bottom of the earth
was a frightful, rotten visage of his wife.
イザナギが地の底で見たのは
腐って恐ろしい形相に  なってしまった妻でした
Even so, is it right to bring back
someone from the dead?
それでも死んだ人を生き返らせるのは 正しいことなの？
We're close to the end of our journey.
旅の終わりは近い
You must decide yourself what you
seek at the Gate of Life and Death.
生死の門で何を求めるかは
アスナ 自分で決めなさい
A light? People?
明かり…人？
いや
No.
Izoku!
夷族
Don't worry,
they shouldn't be able to reach us here.
大丈夫 ここまでは来られないはずだ
この世での役割を終え  次の世界に行く時なのだよ
The part it played in this world is over,
and it is time for it to pass on to the next.
Cry for it all you can.
たくさん泣いておあげ
For her sake, as well...
あのお嬢さんのためにも
What's that?
あれは
It will be here soon.
じきにやって来るじゃろう
Quetzal Coatl!
And a really ancient one, too...
ケツァルト？なんて古い…
And in that way, it becomes
part of an even larger life...
ああやって 命はもっと  大きなものの一部になるのだ
I wonder if Asuna thinks of it that way?
アスナにも そう思えるのでしょうか
Even though something precious
to her has died...
大切な存在が死んでしまったのに
Elder, perhaps it is because the world
of Agartha has learned too much
ご老人
アガルタ世界は現世での命の停さ　意味の乏しさを知りすきている
about how short and meaningless
life is in the present...
Isn't that why it has
begun to fall into ruin?
だからこそ 滅びゆくのではないのですか
Your naiveté is quite similar to
that Topsider man.
そなたの未熟さは よく似ている
あの地上人の男に
They have longbarrels with them!
長筒を提げている
Are they going to stop them,
even if they have to kill them?
殺してでも地上人を止めるか
The same task which you bear.
そなたの負うた役目と同じじゃ
What will you do?
どうする気じゃ
I don't know.
分かりません
But...!
しかし　ご恩は必ず返します
I will repay my debt!
Everyone has left...
皆 行ってしまうな
It's over that ridge.
この尾根の向こうだ  夷族が出る前に急ごう
We must hurry before the Izoku come out.
Asuna...
アスナ
Can you hear that?
何か聞こえませんか？
アモロートの兵だ
The soldiers from Amaurot!
走れ
Run!
Hide! I'll finish this quick.
隠れてなさい すぐに済む
先生
Mr. Morisaki!
They're trying to kill us now!
ヤツらも我々を殺すつもりだ
Shin?
シン
余計なことを
I didn't ask for you to butt in!
誰も殺すな
Don't kill anyone.
You'll just increase Agartha's hatred.
アかレタの憎しみを増すだけだ
The boy from Canaan?
Why do you cover for the Topsiders?
力ナンの村の者か
なぜ地上人をかばう
Those two saved a girl from your village.
この2人は  あなたたちの村の娘を助けた
You should owe them a debt of gratitude!
恩義があるはずだ
If we leave the Topsiders be,
they will become the catalyst for ruin.
地上人を野放しにすることは  滅びの呼び水となろう
We cannot allow this root
of evil in the future.
将来に禍根は残せぬ
どけ
Move!
I've paid back my debt... Go now!
借りは返す 行けえ
Shin!
You're not bad.
手ごわいな
Please, allow me.
やらせてください
It's the end of this world... Finis Terra.
この世の果て フィニス·テラだ
The Gate of Life and
Death is at the bottom of this cliff.
あの岸の底に生死の門がある
Hurry...
Don't let his actions go to waste.
急ごう
彼の行為を無駄にするな
Lose as much weight as you can.
身を軽くしなさい 崖を降りるぞ
We're climbing down to the bottom.
But...
そんな…
I can't! Isn't there some other way...
無理ですどこか他の場所から
そんな暇はない
There's no time for that.
When the sun sets,
the Izoku will come out.
陽が落ちれば夷族が出る
Let's go.
行こう
Mr. Morisaki!
先生
アスナ
Asuna!
Asuna.
アスナ
Listen to me.
よく聞きなさい
You crossed through the Interstitial Sea,
and came this deep into the world.
君は狭間の海を越え  世界のこれほど深くまで来た
I know you will be able to
get past this cliff.
この崖も必ず越えることができる
Remember why you came to Agartha!
君は何のためにアガルタに来たんだ
But... But, this place is...
でも… でも ここは
I... can't do it.
私… できません
Enough of this.
You have lost your place in Agartha.
もうやめておけ  アガルタに居場所を失うぞ
I never had one to begin with!
居場所など もとよりない
わかっだ
I understand. I'll go on alone.
私一人で行く
Hand over the clavis.
In exchange, you carry this.
クラヴィスを渡しなさい
代わりに君はこれを持て
Go back upstream along the river,
and aim for the Elder's place.
川をさかのぼり  老人の所を目指しなさい
夜が来たら水に入り  夷族を避けることだ
When night falls,
enter the water to escape from the Izoku.
アスナ
Asuna. I want you to live.
私は君に 生きてほしいと思っている
I know this is selfish of me,
but please remember that for me.
勝手かもしれないが  できれば それを覚えておいて＜れ
クラヴィスが  フィニス·テラの下に消えた
The clavis has disappeared
down into Finis Terra.
We can pursue it no further.
これ以上は もう追えぬ
But there is no way for the Topsiders
to survive descending that cliff.
だが 地上人は どのみち生きて 岸を降りることはかなうまい
小僧 アガルタにも地上にもつかぬ お前が
Boy, neither Agartha nor the surface
この先 安らげる場所は 一つとしてないだろう
can provide you rest or peace any longer.
You have chosen to wander
aimlessly for all eternity.
永遠に流浪する生き方を お前は選んだのだ
Think on that, and repent.
それを悔い続けるがいい
I'm sorry for forcing you to gallop so far...
Can you stand?
すまなかったな  ここまで無理に走らせすぎた
立てるか？
Where should I go now?
これから どこへ行こうか
Asuna...
アスナ…
Ruins?
遺跡が…
クソ
Damn it!
The defiled...
Kill... Devour...
コロセ クエ
Defiled... Devour...
ケガレダ…
クエ
コロセ
Asuna...
アスナ
祝福をあげる
I'll give you a blessing.
Mom, what's a blessing?
お母さん
祝福って何？
A blessing?
祝福？
"I'll give you a blessing."
祝福をあげるって
Did someone say that to you?
誰かに言われたの？
Yeah...
It's like how happy I was that
you were born, Asuna.
アスナが生まれてきてくれて  よかったってことよ
I think that's a blessing.
私もそう思うわ
Hey, Asuna!
アスナちゃん
Want to walk home together?
一緒に帰ろう
アスナ
Asuna!
I'm sorry about you getting involved, Asuna.
巻き込んで  すまなかったな
アスナ
Why did you save me?
なぜ俺を助けた
Just how solitary human existence is...
人がどれほど孤独な存在なのかを
I will repay my debt!
借りは返す
Asuna!
アスナ
君は…
Why?
Why have you come to Agartha?
君は何のために アガルタに来たんだ？
Why?
なんだ
It's just because...
私…
I was so lonely.
ただ… 寂しかったんだ
No way...
まさか…
Lisa...
リサ…
I'll see you soon.
もうすぐ会える
もうすく…
Soon...
水が引いてる
The water is gone!
When did...
いつの間に？
Defiled...
ケガレダ…
コロセ…
Kill...
ここで待ってろ
Wait here!
Devour the defiled...
ケガレダ 喰ゥ
私…
生き…
I...
I... have to live...
生き… なきゃ
アスナ
Asuna!
The dawn is breaking.
夜が明ける
It's good you're safe, Asuna.
無事でよかったな アスナ
Yeah...
助けてくれてありがとう シン
Thank you for saving me, Shin.
今まで ちゃんとお礼言ったこと なかったよね
I never properly thanked you before,
have I?
Really? My body just moved on its own.
そうか？
体が勝手に動くんだ
考えるより先に
I wasn't really thinking about trying
to save you or anything.
助けようと思っていたわけじゃないさ
What?
何だよ
The color of your eyes is a
little different than Shun's.
目の色がちょっと違うんだね  シュンくんとは
Yeah. And my brother was taller,
and his hair was a slightly different color, too.
ああ 兄さんのほうが背も高かったし
髪の色も少し違う
What are you, a kid?
なんだ 子供じゃない
お前だって子供だろ
So are you!
You really aren't Shun, after all...
やっぱり  シンはシュンくんじゃなかったんだ
Are you still...
お前 まだそんなこと
Because...
だって…
泣くな
Don't cry!
兄さん
Brother...
シャクナ·ヴィマーナ
Shakuna Vimana!
It's heading to the Gate of Life and Death.
生死の門に向かっている
That's where Mr. Morisaki is...
そこって先生が
アルカンジ工リが  たどり着いたのか？
That Arch Angel guy made it?
Vimana is the ark that carries life itself!
ヴィマーナは命を運び去る舟だぞ
Finis Terra!
フィニス·テラ
I thought I'd gotten a lot farther away...
もっとずっと離れたと思ってたのに
I must have gone around in
circles during the night.
闇の中でのレのレ回ってたんだ
Quetzal Coatl!
ケツァルトル
Asuna, this Quetzal Coatl is...
アスナ このケツァルトルは…
You know?
分かるのか？
It's probably come here to die.
たぶん 死にに来たんだ
Vita aqua! This is...
ヴィー夕クアだ
ここは…
A graveyard of Quetzal Coatl!
ケツァルトルの墓場か
This is...
the Gate of Life and Death?
これが…
生死の門
A song?
唄？
Before they die,
the Quetzal Coatl do this...
ケツアルトルは  死ぬ前に ああやって
They sing a song containing
all of their memories.
すべての記憶を唄に込めて残すんだ
This goes out, changing the
form of things everywhere...
唄はどこまでも  形を変えて伝わってゆく
Without us noticing it, the vibrations in the
air enter our bodies and intermix within us.
空気の振動の中に受け継がれ　俺たちの体とも  気づかぬうちに混じり合う
By doing this, they make sure their
memories exist for eternity,
そうやって世界のどこかに　永久に記憶されるそうだ
somewhere within the world.
I've heard this song before.
私 聴いたことがある この唄
It's always stayed within me...
ずっと胸に残ってる
アスナ
Asuna!
Shin, I have to go to Mr. Morisaki.
シン 私 先生の所に行かなくちゃ　一人で困ってるかもしれないもの
I think he might be in trouble alone.
But, the cliff...
でも この岸は…
It says that it will take us there.
この人が連れていってくれるって
Shakuna Vimana!
シャクナ·ヴィマーナ
This is Agartha's... god.
これがアガルタの…
神
State my wish?
願いを言えと
I have never once forgotten these past
ten years, even for an instant.
10年間
ひとときたりとも 忘れたことはない
I once truly tried to get past your death,
but it was no use.
かつて君の死を乗り越えようと 努力もした
だが…ダメなんだ
I cannot find any meaning in
a world without you in it.
君がいない世界に  意味を見いだすことができない
Lisa, return to my side!
リサ 僕の元に戻ってきてくれ
Shin!
シン
星空
Stars!
These are... stars?
これが 星？
Shin, look!
シンあれ
Mr. Morisaki...
先生
Lisa, is that you?
リサ… なのか？
Why...
なぜ…
You say to offer you a living vessel
in which to place her soul?
魂を入れる 肉の器を差し出せと？
先生
Mr. Morisaki!
Asuna...
アスナ
君に この場に  現れてほしくはなかった
I didn't want you to show up here.
Asuna!
アスナ
アスナ どうした？
Asuna, what's the matter?
A soul of the dead is in Asuna's body...
死者の魂をアスナの体に…
アルカンジェリ
You damn Arch Angel!
Did you choose this?
お前が選んだのか
Asuna!
アスナ
心を明け渡すな　戻れな＜なるぞ
Don't give up your heart!
You won't be able to come back!
アスナ アスナ
Asuna, Asuna!
It's cold...
寒いわ…
Where are you?
どこにいるの？
Dear...
あなた…
Lisa!
リサ
So that girl alone wasn't enough?
あの少女だけでは足りないか
Dear...
あなた
アスナ
Asuna...
Dear, are you there?
あなた そこにいるの？
Asuna, snap out of it!
アスナ しっかりしろ
Arch Angel, give Asuna back!
アルカンジェリアスナを戻せ
お前 目を？
Your eye...
It's too late,
I've already paid the price.
もう遅い 代償は支払ってしまった
Lisa...
リサ
I'm right here.
僕は ここにいるよ
Dear...
あなた
What is it?
It looks like you've grown a bit older...
どうしたの？少し年をとったみたい
I'm sorry, Lisa...
すまない リサ
No, Asuna!
ダメだ アスナ
Asuna, come back!
アスナ戻れ
That boy... I know him.
あの子…
Asuna, come back!
私 知ってるわ
Asuna!
Why is it that my heart...
どうしてかしら 胸が…
Lisa, stay here.
リサ 君はここにいて
I'll be right back.
すぐに戻るよ
Asuna!
アスナ
Please, stop this.
もう やめてくれ
Lisa has done nothing wrong!
リサには罪はない
The living are more important!
生きているものが大事だ
シン
Shin?
You're going, right, Asuna?
行くんだね アスナ
Yeah... Farewell.
うん さよなら
Lisa!
リサ
Lisa...
I'm sorry, Dear.
ごめんなさいね あなた
I wasn't able to protect you...
守ってあげられなくて…
Lisa, no...
リサ ダメだ
Don't go...
行くな
Lisa...
リサ
I love you.
愛している
I loved you!
愛していた
Find... happ... iness...
幸せを…
幸せを… さ…が…し…て…
Kill me.
殺せ
Kill me, please.
殺してくれ
I heard a voice telling me to live,
embracing the loss.
喪失を抱えて なお生きろと 声が聞こえた
You should have heard it too.
お前にも聞こえたはずだ
それが人に与えられた呪いだ
It's the curse that we humans must bear.
But I think it's also... a blessing.
でも きっと…
それは祝福でもあるんだと思う
Hello Goodbye&Hello
Hello, goodbye and hello
Kimi ni atte ima kimi to sayonara
君にあって　今君とさよなら
I met you, and now I say goodbye
君に会って 今 君とさよなら
Hello, goodbye and hello
Hello Goodbye&Hello
Soshite kimi no inai kono sekai ni Hello
そして君のいないこの世界で　Hello
And hello to this world without you
そして君のいない この世界にHello
Hontou no sayonara o shiranakatta ano toki
本当のさよならを知らなかったあの時
Back then, I didn't know what it really meant to say goodbye
本当のさよならを知らなかった あの時
壊れゆく心は ずっと君を探してた
Kowareyuku kokoro wa zutto kimi o sagashiteta
壊れ行く心はずっと君を探してた
My breaking heart was always searching for you
Moshimo todoku no naraba
もしも届くのならば
If I could have reached you,
もしも 届くのならば
伝えたかったことが たくさんある
tsutaetakatta koto ga takusan aru
伝えたかったことがたくさんある
there's so much I've wanted to tell you
Subete no kimochi de kimi no egao o
全ての気持ちで君の笑顔を
I vow, with all of my feelings,
tayasazu soba ni itai to chikau yo
絶やさず 側にいたいと誓うよ
to wish your smile would never fade from beside me
絶やさずそばにいたいと誓うよ
Hello, goodbye and hello.
Hello Goodbye&Hello
君に会って 今 君とさよなら
Kimi ni atte ima kimi to sayonara
君にあって　今君とさよなら
I met you, and now I say goodbye
Hello, goodbye and hello
Hello Goodbye&Hello
Soshite kimi no inai kono sekai ni Hello
そして君のいないこの世界で　Hello
And hello to this world without you
そして君のいない この世界にHello
Asuna! Hurry and leave or
you'll be late!
アスナ 早出ないと遅れるわよ
It's the graduation ceremony, after all!
卒業式なんだから
ハーイ
Right!
お母さん
Mom...
I'm heading out!
行ってきます
A
Kimi o suki ni natta toki kara hajimatteita kono tabi
君を好きになった時から始まっていたこの旅
Ever since I fell in love with you, I've started this journey
君を好きになったときから　始まっていた この旅
Hello Goodbye&Hello
Hello, goodbye and hello
Kimi no koto o itsumo wasurenai yo
君のことをいつも忘れないよ
I met you, and I'll never forget you
Hello, goodbye and hello
Hello Goodbye&Hello
そしてこの道を歩いてゆくんだ
Soshite kono michi o aruite yukunda
そしてこの道を歩いて行くんだ
And I'll keep walking along this path
Nakushitakunai negai
無くしたくない願い
The wish I don't want to lose
なくしたくない願い
ichiban tooi hoshi dato omotta yo
一番遠い星だと思ったよ
I thought it was the most distant star
Sora wa hirogaru asu no you ni
空は広がる明日のように
Like the wide open sky of tomorrow,
空は広がる 明日のように
果てないけれど 手を伸ばしたいよ
hatenai keredo te o nobashitai yo
I want to stretch out my hand without end
Hello, goodbye and hello
Hello Goodbye&Hello
君に会って 今 君とさよなら
Kimi ni atte ima kimi to sayonara
君にあって　今君にさよなら
I met you, and now I say goodbye
Hello Goodbye&Hello
Hello, goodbye and hello
Soshite kimi no inai kono sekai ni Hello
そして君のいないこの世界に　Hello
And hello to this world without you
そして君のいない この世界にHello
Hello, goodbye and hello
Hello Goodbye&Hello
君に会って 今 君とさよなら
Kimi ni atte ima kimi to sayonara
君にあって　今君にさよなら
I met you, and now I say goodbye
Hello, goodbye and hello
Hello Goodbye&Hello
Soshite kimi no inai kono sekai ni Hello
そして君のいないこの世界に　Hello
And hello to this world without you
そして君のいない この世界にHello